When it comes to something
as life-and-death important
as what to feed ourselves
and our families,
we should rely not on
anecdotes, but on facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
There’s a lot of research
being done right now
on the best way to understand
the processes by which we age.
Here’s our first story.
There are numerous ways
to try to unlock
the mysteries of aging.
You could study
long-lived individuals
like centenarians
and supercentenarians,
particularly long-lived smokers,
perhaps,
to uncover the secrets
to their resilience.
Or, you could go
in the opposite direction
and study short-lived people—
tragic, accelerated aging
syndromes like progeria,
where children age at eight
to ten times the normal rate,
wrinkling, balding, and then
typically dying around age 13
of a heart attack or stroke.
Or, you could study
long-lived animals.
There are mammals,
such as the bowhead whale,
that can live hundreds of years.
There are oysters and clams
whose hearts can beat
over a billion times
over its five-century lifespan.
What accounts for the
10,000-fold range of lifespan
in the animal kingdom?
Most of the aging pathways
identified
as the hallmarks of aging
were established using
so-called "model organisms,"
such as yeast, worms,
flies, and mice,
simpler species that may
nonetheless offer insights
due to the remarkable
conservation
of common aging mechanisms
through the eons
of evolutionary time.
Aging used to be considered
simply too complex to study,
a constellation of internal
and external influences
too complicated to disentangle.
But then, the game changer,
the discovery
that a single gene mutation
could dramatically prolong
the lifespan and youthful state
of a tiny worm
known as C. elegans.
C. elegans has since
wormed its way
deep into the study
of longevity.
It seems we shared
a common ancestor
about a half billion years ago,
and, to this day,
we still share
about half their genes.
With a lifespan of only
two to three weeks,
their fast turnover allows
researchers to rapidly assess
the effects of genetic
or dietary tweaks,
unlike humans,
who are described as
"not an easy-to-study system
both for ethical as well as
for practical reasons."
Even simpler,
the single-celled organism
Saccharomyces cerevisiae,
otherwise known as brewer's
or baker's yeast.
In 1959, it was discovered that
yeast cells are not immortal,
dividing only
a finite number of times.
They're even more evolutionarily
divergent, though.
We haven't shared a common
ancestor with brewer's yeast
for more like a billion years
and only have about 30 percent
of their genes in common
at this point,
but their microscopic size
and even faster turnover
allows for high-throughput
systems able to screen
through more than a thousand
different compounds a day
for potentially
lifespan-extending properties.
And, even if those
yeast longevity compounds
fail to translate
to extending human life,
yeast researchers argue
they could still be useful
for brewing extra beer.
Yeast have a lifespan
that can be measured in days,
worms in weeks,
fruit flies—
another common model—in months,
compared to mice
that can live for years.
But, mice and men were one
as few as 75 million years ago,
arising
in the mammalian explosion
shortly after the resolution
of the asteroid v. dinosaurs
matchup.
Mice share about 85 percent
of their genes with humans.
Granted,
it's an important 15 percent.
Humans are not just more complex
anatomically than rodents,
but more complex
even on a cellular level.
Extrapolating data
from lab animals
is infamously fraught
with difficulty.
Fewer than one in ten cancer
drugs that seem to work in mice
even make it
into human clinical trials,
and hundreds of seemingly
promising Alzheimer's drugs
have similarly been
lost in translation.
As one review in the journal
Trends in Biotechnology put it:
"Humans Are Not Huge Worms
or Big Mice."
We are, however, big primates.
Rhesus monkeys are also used
in aging research,
though can live
up to 40 years,
stretching research timelines.
Their DNA is 93 percent
identical to humans,
though as similarity increases,
so too do ethical concerns
regarding experimentation.
One might expect
research on dogs
to perhaps be most sensitive,
but there are
citizen science initiatives
in which family dogs are
enrolled in noninvasive studies
to study, for example,
the genetics of why some
so-called "methuselah dogs"
reach ages of 25 or more,
but 99.9 percent
of other dogs do not.
For example, mixed-breed dogs
live more than a year longer
than same-size purebred dogs,
who can be plagued
with certain genetic disorders.
Aged pooches suffer many
of the same ravages of aging:
arthritis, cancer, cataracts,
kidney problems, muscle loss,
et cetera.
Advances in canine longevity
might not only be applicable
to human aging
but have the intrinsic value
of enhancing the quality
and quantity of life
of the more than
70 million companions
we share our homes with
in the U.S. alone.
In our next story,
we look at ways to boost the
longevity hormone FGF21.
In the year 2000, a new human
hormone was discovered.
It was the 21st documented
fibroblast growth factor;
so, they called it FGF21.
Since its discovery, FGF21 has
emerged as a key agent for
promotion of metabolic and artery
health, leanness, and longevity.
Inject it into fat monkeys,
and they lose body weight
without reducing food intake,
and not just a little—
a 27 percent drop in body fat
eating the same amount.
In mice, it increases their
lifespan 30 to 40 percent,
comparable to lifelong caloric
restriction, but again
was achieved without
decreasing food intake.
The researchers conclude that
FGF21 could potentially be
used as a hormone therapy to
extend lifespan in mammals,
which has gotten big pharma
salivating, raising the question
“Can aging be ‘drugged’?”
And that’s not all it can do.
The idea that one drug
can treat obesity, diabetes,
dyslipidemia (like high
cholesterol), and hypertension
all at once might have
seemed impossible a few years ago
but is now a tantalizing
and exciting prospect.
The reason you can’t just give
people straight FGF21 is that
it gets rapidly broken down in the body;
so, you’d have to get injections like
every hour or two around the clock.
So, drug companies are
trying to patent a variety of
longer-acting FGF21 look-alikes.
And indeed, give people
a little PF-05231023
and they can lose about
10 pounds in 25 days,
along with dramatic drops in
triglycerides and cholesterol.
But then, the side effects
of these new-fangled drugs
started cropping up.
Okay, so what about this:
we package the FGF21 gene into
a virus and then inject the virus
and have it stitch extra
FGF21 genes into our DNA.
Or you can just lace
on your running shoes.
Exercise boosts FGF21 levels,
which may in fact
be one of the reasons
exercise is so good for us.
Which works better, though,
aerobic exercise—eight weeks
of running training—or resistance
exercise—eight weeks of weights?
The answer is both, but the
resistance exercise edged out
the running, a 42 percent
increase in FGF21 versus
a 25 percent increase in
the aerobic exercise group.
Okay, but what can we do with food?
Yeah, you could try
engineering and injecting it,
but wouldn’t it be easier to
just stimulate our own endogenous,
natural production through diet?
One way is through no diet at all.
You may have noticed it’s been
dubbed the starvation hormone.
That’s because fasting induces
FGF21, but not just a day or two.
Physiologically, FGF21
expression is markedly increased
in response to fasting/starvation.
But, unlike mice, which
show an increase after
just six hours of fasting,
humans don’t get a notable surge
in FGF21 until after a week.
Fasting can quadruple FGF21,
but it takes 10 days of fasting,
which is the very poster child of
an unsustainable eating pattern.
Finally today,
what can physicians do to promote healthy,
life-extending, lifestyle changes?
Here’s the story.
A pivotal paper published in
Europe more than a decade ago
entitled “Healthy Living Is
the Best Revenge” found that
adhering to just four simple
healthy lifestyle factors
compared to none could
potentially have a strong impact
on the prevention
of chronic diseases;
we’re talking nearly 80 percent
less chronic disease risk,
slashing diabetes
risk by 93 percent,
dropping heart attack
risk by 81 percent,
and cutting stroke risk in half,
and cancer by 36 percent.
Think about what that means.
The potential for preventing
disease and death is enormous.
In the U.S. alone every year,
there are half million
heart attacks, half million
strokes, a million new cases
of diabetes, and a
million new cancer diagnoses.
The message is clear:
adopting a few healthy behaviors
can have a major impact.
What are those four fabled factors?
Never smoking, not being obese,
averaging about a half hour of
exercise a day, and adhering to
healthy dietary principles,
like lots of fruits, vegetables,
and whole grains, and less meat.
Follow those four
simple rules and boom!
Enjoy nearly 80 percent reduced
risk of major chronic diseases.
What does that mean
for mortality risk?
A similar batch of four healthy
behaviors combined predicted
a four-fold difference
in total mortality,
with an estimated impact
equivalent to 14 years
in chronological age, meaning
the individuals were dying at
such a reduced rate that it was
as if they were 14 years younger.
“Finally, a Regimen to
Extend Human Life Expectancy.”
This commentary was in
reference to this study,
where a similar analysis
of the impact of healthy
lifestyle behaviors on
life expectancies was made,
but this time it looked
directly at the U.S. population,
which is particularly important,
since Americans have a
shorter life expectancy
compared with residents
of nearly all other
high-income countries.
The researchers concluded that
adopting a healthy lifestyle
could substantially
reduce premature mortality
and prolong life
expectancy in U.S. adults.
Okay, but by how much?
They estimated that adherence
to a low-risk lifestyle
could prolong life expectancy
at age 50 by 14 years
in women and 12.2 years in men.
So, if you’re 50 right now,
instead of only living to 79
if you’re a woman, and
75½ if you’re a man,
taking even just basic care
of yourself could propel you
to an average life expectancy
of 93 if you’re a woman
and 87½ if you’re a man.
The bottom line is it’s never
too late to turn back the clock.
A midlife switch just
to the basics, like at least
five servings fruits
and vegetables a day,
walking even like 20 minutes a day,
maintaining a healthy
weight, and not smoking
results in a substantial
reduction in mortality
even in the following few years.
We’re talking a 40 percent
lower risk of dying
in the subsequent four years.
So, making the necessary
changes to adhere to a healthy
lifestyle could be considered
extremely worthwhile,
and middle age is certainly
not too late to act.
As an aside, realizing the
12 to 14 years of added life
study was based on data
from health professionals,
that got me excited about
all the potential knock-on effects.
If health professionals
start getting healthier,
they could become role models
for more healthful living
and potentially save more
lives than just their own.
But that may have just
been wishful thinking.
Practicing what you preach
can sometimes backfire.
Evidently, “displays of excellence
can paradoxically turn off
the very people they
are trying to inspire.”
You’d assume that not
being a hypocrite and trying
to walk the walk would just
lead to positive consequences,
inspiring confidence in others, right?
Don’t you want a dance instructor
who can dance, a music teacher
who can play, a health
professional who’s healthy?
But this simple intuition
fails to take into account
concerns about making
other people feel inadequate.
Like you know how vegetarians
are the targets of a
surprising amount of
hostility and ridicule.
That’s because they may
come off as morally superior
and make people feel like
they’re being looked down upon.
There was an elegant
demonstration of this phenomenon
in this study where
“Principled deviants who take
the high road threaten
others’ moral self-worth.”
This is what they did.
Research subjects were asked
to complete a racist
task by an experimenter,
and those moral rebels who
refused to obey were cheered
by observers but were
disparaged by participants
who had themselves
gone through with it,
and for whom the rebel’s stance
thus implied an indictment
of their spinelessness.
Isn’t that interesting?
So, when doctors portray themselves
as “the picture of health,”
patients might think they’re
being holier-than-thou and
unintentionally alienate people,
potentially turning off
the very patients who
most need their help.
You can see how someone with
a weight issue might feel
threatened and judged
by a physician triathlete.
But what are we supposed to do?
We want healthy practitioners.
Physicians who
smoke are less likely
to tell their patients
to quit smoking,
physicians who are overweight
are less likely to counsel
their patients about weight,
and physicians
who don’t work out
are less likely to
talk about exercise.
What we can do to make
patients more comfortable
is emphasize that our
role is to help people
meet their own personal health
goals, whatever they may be.
Studies show that when doctors
do this, take this approach,
it increases the appeal of
fitness-focused physicians
to overweight patients.
So, we can then display
exemplary behavior
while at the same time
not inadvertently alienate
the very people who could
benefit most from our guidance.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
I actually just came out
with another small book:
an easy 100-page read on
Ozempic and other GLP-1 drugs.
Go to NutritionFacts.org
and click on “Books”
to see where you can get an e-book,
audiobook, or paperback of it.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.